Okay, good afternoon, wherever you are.
好的，下午好，无论你在哪里。
Um, can everybody hear me,
嗯，大家都能听到我说话吗，
quick sound check, make sure.
快速测试一下语音。
Yeah you're fine.
是的，是好的。
Good, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
So today we're going to talk about,
那么今天我们就来谈一谈，
I don't really have a specific agenda
我没有具体的日程安排，
but basically the plan is to try to answer questions
但基本上我们的计划是回答问题，
that you might have about these last lab or the previous labs.
你可能对上一个实验或之前的实验有什么问题。
Um, so the approach I'm going to take,
所以我要采取的方法是，
today, is, I'm gonna walk through the staff solutions.
今天，我要介绍一下我们的解决方案。
In particularly my own solutions,
尤其是我自己的解决方案，
I'm going to discuss them
我会讨论一下它们，
and hopefully as we go through the staff solutions,
希望在我们讨论解决方案时，
um, you can jump in
你可以打断，
if I don't answer a particular question,
如果我没有回答某个问题，
um or, wait a little bit,
或者稍等一下，
because I put all the questions that you've asked
因为我把你们问的所有问题，
at least before eleven am this morning,
至少在今天上午 11 点之前的，
in the lecture notes at the bottom
在最后的课堂讲稿中，
and we'll try to go through that.
我们会试着去全部过一遍。
I'm gonna start with the pagetable lab,
我将从页表（pagetable）实验开始，
because most questions were about the pagetable lab,
因为大多数问题都是关于页表的实验，
and partly because it was the hardest labs.
部分原因是因为它是最难的实验。
Um, and so maybe a couple of comments
所以也许首先有几点解释，
before diving into the technical part of this,
在深入到技术部分之前，
let's talk a little bit about the pagetable lab in general.
我们来大体上谈一下页表实验。
And you know as you probably observed,
正如你可能观察到的，
you know it's actually a few lines of code,
它实际上只有几行代码，
in terms of the solution,
在解决方案上，
but, it unfortunately has, you know, had to debug problems.
但是，不幸的是，必须调试问题。
And, you know, there's one reason is that
而且，有一个原因是，
when actually bug shows up,
当 bug 真的出现时，
you know the outcomes are pretty extreme
结果是相当极端的，
like in the worst case,
就像在最坏的情况下，
probably some of you observed that the worst case,
可能你们中的一些人观察到了最坏的情况，
QEMU stops or xv6 stops,
QEMU 停止或 xv6 停止，
there's no output being printed anymore, and that's it,
不再打印输出，就是这样，
you know it's your job to figure out actually what went wrong,
你的工作就是找出到底哪里出了问题，
in the best case you get sort of kernel panic,
在最好的情况下，你会遇到某种内核错误（kernel panic），
depending you know maybe just a starting point
取决于，也许这只是一个起点，
or for tracking down what the actual source of the problem is panic itself,
或者追查问题的真正根源是错误本身，
it's probably related to something else,
可能与其他什么有关，
something the invariant that the kernel got broken,
内核的一些常量被破坏，
but you know somewhere out earlier,
但你知道早些时候在外面的某个地方，
probably when you set up the pagetables,
可能在设置页表时，
you did something wrong at the end causes panic to go off,
你做错了什么最后引起错误，
you have to track down what's going on.
你得追踪到底是怎么回事。
So fewer lines of code, hard to debug problems,
所以代码行数更少，很难调试问题，
in produce a harsh environment, to debug.
在生产环境，恶劣的环境中去调试。
If you do in the kernel debugging or kernel programming,
如果你做内核调试或内核编程，
you know programming environment, debugging environment,
你知道，编程环境，调试环境，
is more, you know unforgiven,
更是，你知道的，恶劣的，
as Robert mentioned in the first lecture,
正如 Robert 在第一节课中提到的，
is one of the hard parts about basically doing kernel programming.
是做内核编程的难点之一。
And that's you know just to make you feel better,
为了让你感觉好点，
this is not just hard for you,
这不仅对你来说很难，
you know actually hard for your staff.
你知道对我们来说也很难。
Both in terms of helping you
无论是在帮助你方面，
and actually you know we do these labs
实际上我们做这些实验，
and we make similar problems,
我们也会遇到类似的问题，
you know we probably have more experience at tracking bugs down,
我们可能有更多的经验追踪 bug ，
but you know they just, they do take time.
但是你知道它们确实需要时间。
Um, so we're helping you,
所以我们在帮你的时候，
you know the, tends to be hard too,
往往也很难，
because there's some small fragment of code,
因为有一些很小的代码片段，
there's one detail something probably wrong
有一个细节可能有问题，
and they're figuring out actually what little detail is,
他们要弄清楚到底什么是小细节，
it's not easy.
这并不容易。
Of course some of the problems,
当然有一些问题，
we've seen before and we're recognizing,
我们以前见过，我们也认识到，
for example we didn't make the same mistake ourselves,
例如，我们自己没有犯同样的错误，
but other ones you discovered
但是你们发现的其他一些，
all kinds of different ways of breaking the kernel,
各种不同的破坏内核的方式，
that we hadn't seen before.
我们以前没见过的。
So this is just hard,
所以这很难，
I think this is, in our experience,
根据我们的经验，
this is historically always hard with virtual memory,
对于虚拟内存，这在以往也总是很难，
so every time the first virtual memory lab comes around,
所以每次第一个虚拟内存实验出现的时候，
either in 6.S081 or its predecessor in 6.828,
不论在 6.S081 中或它的前身 6.828 中，
it has been the case
事实就是这样
that you know that tends to be the hardest lab,
你知道那往往是最难的实验，
of all the labs
在所有实验室中，
and you know for a number of reasons,
你知道的，原因有很多，
one you know the harsh environment,
一种是恶劣环境，
you know the the bugs are spectacular
这些 bug 很特殊，
and partly because you haven't done
还有部分原因是你还没有
that much kernel programming experience yet,
很丰富的内核编程经验，
and so this is sort of the first lab
所以这可以说是第一个实验，
with all those things come together.
所有这些都结合在一起了。
This year, we tried to make lab simpler,
今年，我们试着让实验变得更简单，
in fact, this is a new lab,
事实上，这是一个新的实验，
a lab we did not have that lab.
一个我们之前没有的实验。
In the hopes that actually
希望实际上，
make this introduction or the transition into a virtual memory easier,
使引入或转换到虚拟内存变得更容易，
in some ways I think it was successful,
在某些方面我认为是成功的，
in other ways, you know it's still hard,
在其他方面，这仍然很难，
so we don't really know,
所以我们不太清楚，
maybe about the easiest way
什么是最简单的方法，
of actually introducing virtual memory programming is.
引入虚拟内存编程。
Lab, the lab next week, the lazy lab
下周的惰性分配实验，
is actually a lab that used to be the first virtual memory lab.
实际上曾经是第一个虚拟内存实验。
And my suspicion is that you'll find this year,
我猜你们今年会发现，
lab easier than the students found it last year,
实验比去年的要容易，
because you now have much more background in virtual memory.
因为你现在在虚拟内存方面有了更多的背景知识。
Okay, so that's, there is a good point to stop,
好的，所以这是一个很好的停止点，
this was a couple high level points I wanted to make,
这里我想提出的几个高层次的观点，
before jumping into more technical with more details,
在跳到更具技术性和更多细节之前，
so if you have any questions, is a great time to ask questions.
所以，如果你有任何问题，现在就是提问题的好时机。
Okay.
好的。
Let's, quickly, you know some of you asked for this,
让我们，快点，你知道，你们中的一些人问到这个，
very quick review exactly what you were what the setting is,
非常快速地回顾一下具体设置是什么，
and so, basically, the settings pagetables,
所以，基本上，设置页表，
and we have physical memory draw here, right side,
我们在右边画出物理内存，
you know the physical memory, consist of partly about devices,
你知道物理内存，包含部分设备，
and they live above this 0x zero zero and many more zeros,
它们在这个 0x00 以及更多的零之上，
and then here basically dram chips.
然后这里是 DRAM 芯片。
And we know that
我们知道，
QEMU actually puts the kernel, the kernel text data, right here,
QEMU 将内核文本数据放在这里，
at the above 0x zero zero zero,
在 0x00 之上，
so that's where the kernel lives,
这就是内核所在的地方，
and one way it may be,
其中一种可能是，
earse this a little bit to use the kernel.
擦掉这个来使用内核。
And you know basically literally what it means,
你知道从字面上它是什么意思，
you know what this is what the kernel is user instructions,
你知道这是什么，内核就是用户指令，
binary versions of the assembling instructions that you've seen,
是你已经看到的汇编指令的二进制版本，
and there's also some data structures located at these addresses.
还有一些数据结构位于这些地址。
Okay, so that's the memory part of it
好的，这就是内存的部分，
and then on the other side we got our CPU,
然后在另一边，我们有 CPU ，
that executes instructions.
它执行指令。
CPU has a bunch of internal state,
CPU 有很多内部指令，
and has some registers,
并且有一些寄存器，
you know whatever x0 or r0 blah blah blah,
你知道 x0 或 r0 等，
and you know maybe the program counter.
还有程序计数器。
And you know when xv6 starts,
你知道在 xv6 启动的时候，
you know the program counter contains this value Ox8000.
程序计数器包含值 Ox8000 。
And that's the way you know,
这就是它的方式，
the CPU knows that basically look at that address
CPU 查看这个地址，
to find you know the first instruction,
找出第一条指令，
it looks at the first instruction decode instruction
它查看第一个指令并解码指令，
and updates whatever CPU state that needs to be updated.
然后更新需要更新的 CPU 状态。
You know pagetables and sort of component to it
页表和其他一些组件，
that you know the addresses you know
这个地址包含，
the CPU orders or the instructions are part of the instructions,
CPU 命令或指令，
like you know jump to some particular address
比如，跳到某个特定的地址，
and those addresses are typically or most commonly or will be virtual addresses.
并且这些地址通常是虚拟地址。
And now there's virtual addresses, go to that [] is called the MMU.
这是虚拟地址，由 MMU 管理。
And then you translate into physical addresss,
然后转换成物理地址，
um, and that is allowing [] index into
并且索引到
either the IO part of the memory
内存的 IO 部分，
or the DRAM part the memory.
或者内存的 DRAM 部分。
To control how this translation happens,
为了控制这个转换发生，
you know there's this satp register,
你知道这里有 satp 寄存器，
which contains the root of the pagetable
它包含页表的根地址，
of the current running page table.
即当前运行的页表。
And if there's zero,
如果是零，
then there's basically no translation going on
那么就不会进行转换，
and the virtual address is literally directly physical address,
并且虚拟地址直接指向物理地址，
so when the processor actually starts up,
因此，当处理器启动时，
there's no value in satp
satp 中没有值，
and when the program counter as an 0x...,
当程序计数器是 0x... 时，
you know basically the physical address is also []
物理地址也是[]，
and basically [] the CPU fetches the instruction from that particular location.
CPU 从该特定位置获取指令。
As soon as you know the,
一旦，
as soon as the satp actually contains a non zero value,
一旦 satp 包含非零值，
then, you know, for example maybe so somewhere in here
那么，例如，可能，在这里的某个地方，
to draw them make something extended pictures a bit further,
把图片延伸一些，
we know that the kernel actually has a maximum 128 megabytes.
我们知道内核实际上最多有 128 兆字节。
And so basically this is all free memory,
所以基本上这些都是空闲内存，
from here to there is free memory
从这里到这里是空闲内存，
and free memory is put on the list in kalloc.c
空闲内存放在 kalloc.c 中的列表中，
as you've seen before.
像你之前看到的那样。
And, so somewhere in here is also the root pagetable
并且，这里的某个地方也是根页表，
for you know a kernel pagetable,
你知道的，内核页表，
so maybe here's some page,
可能这里有一些页面，
and that it's the root pagetable directory.
是根页表目录。
As soon as we load that value
一旦我们加载该值，
the address of the physical address of that value
该值对应的物理地址，
into the satp address and register,
进入 satp 地址和寄存器，
let's say this maybe this addresses 0x7 you know f f blah blah,
假设这个地址是 0x7ff... ，
something just below one hundred twenty megabytes,
一个低于 120 兆字节的地址，
so in that free space of memory
所以在内存空闲空间中，
below that address in satp,
在 satp 中地址，
then, at that point you know the processor or MMU
然后，在这时，处理器或 MMU
will use the root pagetables to actually
将使用根页表执行
do the translation from virtual to physical address.
从虚拟地址到物理地址的转换。
And you can think of this, this particular whole thing,
你可以把这整个东西，
sort of being a single sort of box,
像是一个盒子，
you know integrated you know, together.
你知道，将它们整合在一起。
And you have questions about this high-level picture,
你对这张高层次图片有问题吗，
before keep them going,
在继续之前，
so one of the key points to remember here is
所以这里要记住的一个关键点是，
that the page statements themselves also live in memory.
页面状态本身也驻留在内存中。
Okay.
好吧。
Okay, so let's jump down to,
好的，那我们跳到，
the first part of the pagetable lab,
页表实验的第一部分，
namely part one where you have to
也就是第一部分，
print the pagetable for the init program,
为 init 程序打印页表，
and um, and you know explain it basically in terms of this figure three four
你知道的，解释基本上都在图 3.4 ，
and figure three four is right here.
图 3.4 就在这里。
Figure three four,
图 3.4 ，
and this is figure three four shows the user address space,
这是图 3.4 ，显示用户地址空间，
just let's look at the user address space for a second,
让我们看看的用户地址空间，
before we are going to detail,
在进入细节之前，
so we have the text at the bottom,
我们在底部有文本，
so this is the instructions of the program,
这就是程序的指令，
starting address zero
从地址 0 开始，
above the instructions are data, global variables, live there,
上方是数据、全局变量，驻留在那里，
then there's something called the guard page we'll talk about,
然后我们会讨论守护页，
and then it's the stack of the user program,
然后是用户程序的堆栈，
so the kernel has its own stack,
内核有自己的堆栈，
multiple stack
多个堆栈，
user program has its own stack
用户程序有自己的堆栈，
and buff again is basically what's called heap memory, free memory,
缓冲区，也就是所谓堆内存，空闲内存，
you know we can get more memory using sbrk,
我们可以使用 sbrk 获得更多内存，
so sbrk basically points to the top of the user address space,
sbrk 基本上指向用户地址空间的顶部，
we want to grow it,
我们想要增加它，
we called sbrk system call to grow
我们调用 sbrk 系统调用
grow the top of the, to grow the bottom part,
来增加底部部分，
you know up into the heap,
你知道增加到堆里去，
we also know that the top, there from the last lecture,
我们还从上一节课中知道，顶端，
that there are two pages,
有两个页面，
two special pages the trampoline and the trapframe page.
两个特别的页面， trampoline 和 trapframe 页面。
And the trampoline page, you know contains the instructions to the basically,
trampoline 页包含了命令，
transition in and out of the kernel,
进出内核的转换的命令，
the trapframe is a convenient place,
trapframe 是一个很方便的地方，
you know to stores from state and when we jump into the kernel,
存储一些状态，当我们跳入内核时，
because we need the kernel once use registers,
因为我们就需要内核，一旦使用寄存器，
we can use the registers,
我们可以使用寄存器，
because the user space program still has some in use.
因为用户空间程序还有一些在使用。
I'm not gonna talk much about tramframe and trampoline at all,
我不会太多谈论 tramframe 和 trampoline ，
you know they are there.
你知道的，它们在这里。
OK, so here this picture a little below,
好的，在这张图片的下面一点，
you know is actually there, printout from,
你知道就在那里，是打印出来的，
when I run it, from init.
当我运行它时，从 init 打印出来的。
This the first successful call of exec right,
这是 exec 的第一次成功调用，
so we know that init code makes some system call exec,
我们知道 init 代码中有一些 exec 系统调用，
for the program init and just at the end of the exec,
对于程序 init ，正好在 exec 的末尾，
we're printing out that pagetable.
我们打印出那个页表。
And so a couple things that we, many things we can observe,
有几个我们可以观察到的东西，
about this particular pagetable,
关于这个特殊的页表，
so first of all you know,
首先，
we in addition to printing out the physical ptes
除了打印出物理 pte ，
and the physical address is also printing out the flags.
物理地址也打印出了标志。
And you can see here that here flag is one,
你可以看到，这里的标志是 1 ，
and basically says this translation,
基本上就是这个转换，
or this, intermediate page is that similar here,
或者这个中间页像这个一样，
you know is valid independent page,
是有效的独立页，
and this basically corresponds to the level two page
这对应于二级页面，
and then the second one corresponds to the level....
然后第二个对应于……。
I'm sorry I just threw the arrows wrong,
我很抱歉我刚才画错了箭头，
so that's why a pause for a second.
所以我暂停一下。
At the top, this is the top level pagetable,
在顶端，这是顶层页表，
this, you know points to this particular pagetable,
这个，指向这个特定的页表，
and this points to that particular pagetable.
这个，指向那个特定的页表。
Or that's the address, we're pointing to a sort of shorthand for saying,
或者这就是地址，我们使用一种速记，用来表示，
that is the base address for that particular page.
这是特定页面的基础地址。
And you know these pages 4096 bytes,
你知道，这些页面有 4096 字节，
it's size of page size,
大小是页的大小，
and so divided by 64 its going to get 512 entries.
除以 64 会得到 512 个条目。
Okay so we'll see is the bottom part of this address space.
好的，我们看这个地址空间的底部部分。
You know, for init basically has actually all this, has three pages, only three pages,
对于 init ，实际上只有有三个页面，
and we do a couple things
我们做几件事，
that we can discern from the three pages.
可以把这三页区分出来。
We know that the bottom page which basically corresponds to the virtual address zero,
我们知道，底部页面对应虚拟地址零，
this physical address, you know eight seven six four zero.
这个物理地址， 87f640 。
And you know from our previous picture,
你可以从我们之前的图片中知道，
that is somewhere in that free memory,
那就在空闲内存中的某个地方，
that the kernel has available to allocate pages from.
内核可以从中分配页面。
And the final things you see the flags,
最后你看到的是标志，
we see the flags one f,
我们看到标志 1f ，
so it means that read bit set,
所以它意味着读取位设置，
valid bit set, read bit set, w bit set, execute bit set and u bit set,
有效位设置，读取位设置，写位设置，执行位设置，用户位设置，
so this page can contain both data and text,
所以这个页面可以同时包含数据和文本，
and these permissions allow the user program
这些权限允许用户程序
to execute instructions from or to the right memory,
在对应的内存执行指令，
and do it from user space.
并从用户空间执行。
Okay, so then maybe the most interesting question is
好的，那么也许最有趣的问题是，
like what's up with page one.
第一页有什么问题。
And you know as a hint,
作为一个提示，
you know see that page one only has f
你知道，第一页只有 f ，
and not the u bit set.
而没有设置 u 标志位。
So, you know what is the page one.
所以，你知道第一页是什么吗。
Anybody.
有人知道吗。
Is it the guard page.
是不是守护页。
Yeah, it's the guard page right.
是的，是守护页。
So the guard page is mapped,
守护页映射到，
because it has a v in it,
因为它包含 v 标志，
but it has not u bit set,
而没有设置 u 标志，
so any user instruction that tries to,
所以任何用户指令试图，
so if a user program runs off its stack,
因此，如果用户程序运行超过它的堆栈，
so the stack grows from the top down,
堆栈从顶部向下增长，
so even if it actually has more,
所以即使它真的有更多，
stack is big enough for 4096 are completely full,
堆栈足够大，可以容纳 4096 ，
and then user program, you know puts something on the stack,
然后用户程序，你知道的，把东西放到到堆栈上，
stack on the [], it will grow into the guard page.
堆栈在[]上，它将增长到守护页。
And because the u bit is not set,
并且因为没有设置 u 标志位，
we gotta get a page fault or a trap into the kernel,
我们会在内核中得到页面错误或陷阱，
because the MMU cannot translate to address to,
因为 MMU 不能转换地址到，
cannot address cannot translate any addresses on the guard page to physical address,
不能将守护页上的地址转换为物理地址，
because the [] not having a u bit
因为没有设置 u 标志位，
basically forbids the translation.
这会禁止转换。
Okay, what is that page two.
好的，第二页是什么。
Any, Anybody.
有人知道吗？
Stack?
堆栈？
Yup, that's the stack page
是的，这是堆栈页，
and so again the stack page for forty four thousand ninety six bytes
堆栈页有 4096 字节，
and you'll see that's completely elaborate in terms of permissions.
你会看到，对于权限，这是精心设计的。
And it has you know everything,
它包含所有权限，
could we set it up tighter if we wanted to.
我们能不能把它的权限调得更严格一些。
Yeah I think you could disable the executive bit.
是的，我想可以禁用执行位。
Yeah, you probably could execute the x bit,}
是的，你可以，对 x 位来说，
that would forbid run any program code on the stack.
这将禁止运行堆栈上任何程序代码。
So if you generate code on the fly and put it on the stack,
所以，如果你在运行时生成代码并将其放入堆栈，
you wouldn't to be able to execute,
你就不能去执行，
you know that maybe probably a good thing.
你知道这可能是件好事。
And so we could have been a little bit tighter.
所以我们可以把权限设置更严格一些。
Okay, um.
好的。
So that's basically the bottom part of this,
所以这是这个的最下面的部分，
the pagetable,
页表，
so now let's look at the remaining entries,
现在让我们来看看剩下的条目，
so basically only two remaining entries.
只剩下两个条目了。
And maybe the flag bits are the most telling part of this.
也许标志位是最能说明问题的部分。
So seven, you know means you know read write and valid work.
这里的 7 ，表示可读，可写，可用。
And so what do we think, that one is
那么这个是什么，
and maybe I'll do the other one too,
也许我先分析另一个页的权限，
so b is I think one zero zero one,
b 是 1001 （误：应该是 1011），
so presumably x and valid,
设置了 x 和可用位，
so what do we think five eleven is.
那么 511 是什么呢？
Anybody.
有人知道吗。
The trampoline and trap page?
trampoline 和 trap 页面？
Yeah so the, and probably five eleven is definitely trampoline correct,
对，那么， 511 可能是 trampoline ，
because it has the x bit set,
因为它设置了 x 位，
so we must be executed
所以我们可以执行，
or we're allowing instructions to be executed from that page.
或者我们允许从该页面执行指令。
So that must be a trampoline
所以这一定是 trampoline ，
and we're allowing read write you know to the to that page,
我们允许对那个页面进行读写，
so that's probably the trapframe page,
所以这可能就是 trapframe 页面，
because that's the one we used to restore and save registers in.
因为这是我们用来恢复和保存寄存器的那个页。
Okay, one of the things, a important thing to note is
好的，需要注意的一件重要的事是，
there's no u bit right then,
这里没有设置 u 标志位，
so what does that mean,
那么这意味着什么呢，
that means that the user program can actually not execute the instructions,
这意味着用户程序不能执行指令，
that are actually at five ten as a trampoline page,
页 510 作为 trampoline 页面，
and can't be the write to that page.
也不能对该页的写入。
So only the kernel can execute instructions from there
因此，只有内核可以从那里执行指令，
and it can only read and write.
而且它只能读写。
So basically like the kernel's gonna be doing this before the,
所以内核要做这件事，
while still using the user pagetable,
当用户页表还在使用时，
right, that's kind of the point.
是不是这个意思。
Exactly as you know, Robert explained last lecture,
使得，正如你所知道的， Robert 在上节课中讲解的，
this is like just for the transition from user to kernel,
这就是从用户到内核的过渡，
and before we jump to,
在我们跳到之前，
before we load the kernel pagetable in satp register,
在我们将内核页表加载到 satp 寄存器之前，
we need a little bit of,
我们需要，
you know the kernel needs a little bit of memory to actually do his job.
内核需要一些内存来完成它的工作。
Okay.
好的。
So in a couple of things,
所以在一些事情上，
then maybe interesting of this picture.
这张图片有意思的地方。
Yeah, so we all in all these addresses go eight seven six three zero,
是的，所有的地址都是 87f630 ，
eight six two, four, seven one of,
87f620 ， 87f640 ， 87f610 ，
these are all pages or memory
这些页面或内存
in that range of kernel memory
在内核内存范围内，
that is you know it's basically free, right.
它们是空闲的。
And are these addresses are contiguous in physical memory.
那么这些地址在物理内存中是连续的吗？
Anybody.
有人知道吗。
No they don't have to be.
不是，它们不一定连续。
No, they don't have to be in the are, correct,
不，它们不一定连续，是的，
you know look at this, you know seven six four zero zero,
你知道吗，看这个， 87f6400 ，
if it contiguous,
如果是连续的，
the next address would have been eight seven six you know six five zero,
下一个地址应该是 87f6500 ，
and it isn't it.
但事实并非如此。
So there's you know one of the cool things about pagetables is
所以关于页表的一个很酷的事情是，
that even though maybe you do virtual address space is contiguous,
尽管你使用的虚拟地址空间是连续的，
the physical address space
物理地址空间，
or the physical pages that go along with a continuous virtual addresses
或与连续虚拟地址对应的物理页面，
are not don't have to be continuous.
不一定是连续的。
So this gives the kernel a lot of flexibility
因此，这给了内核很大的灵活性，
in terms of allocation and freeing pages.
在分配和释放页面方面。
Okay.
好的。
Any questions about this part one.
关于第一部分，有什么问题吗。
I had a question.
我有一个问题。
Yeah.
嗯。
Could you explain the sbrk a little,
你能稍微解释一下 sbrk 吗，
also if we are going to cover in a future lecture,
如果我们要在未来的讲座中介绍，
then maybe we can like just a small.
那么也许我们可以先讲一点。
Yeah actually we, let me,
对，其实我们，
I'm going to talk about it on Wednesday.
我将在星期三谈论它。
And it actually will be the topic of the lazy lab.
这实际上是惰性分配实验的话题。
So let me maybe responed the question to Wednesday,
那么我可能在星期三回答这个问题，
and then that's not clear enough, please ask it again.
如果到时候还不太清楚，请再问一遍。
Sounds good, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
So had a question.
有一个问题。
So, I remember that the book said
所以，我记得书上说，
trampoline and the trapframe were at the top of the address space.
trampoline 和 trapframe 位于地址空间的顶部。
Right here, it stops at like the first the root pagetable
而在这里，它位于第一个根页面，
indexes at two five five not five one one.
索引是 255 而不是 511 。
Yeah brilliant question, very good, I'm glad you asked.
好问题，很好，很高兴你问我。
I saw in the Q&A questions and I was planning to talk about it,
我在 Q&A 问题中看到了，我打算讨论一下，
but of course I've forgot.
但是，我忘了。
So yeah what's going on here,
所以，是的，这里发生了什么，
why is two five five not five eleven.
为什么是 255 而不是 511 。
Yeah, we always say the trampoline lives at the top of the address space,
我们总说 trampoline 位于地址空间的顶端，
while the top of the address space where it is,
它所在的地址空间的顶部，
you know point is actually entry five eleven of the top level directory,
你知道的，指向顶级目录的 511 条目，
and it is only two five five.
而现在只是 255 。
Anybody any ideas why this is the case.
有人知道为什么是这样吗？
We said that one bit
我们说过有一位，
that we said we were gonna use we actually aren't using,
我们要用但其实没有使用的，
because of sign extension problems is just makes it easier
因为符号扩展问题，也是为了让它变得更容易，
and we also don't need that memory.
并且我们不需要那么多内存。
Yeah, so that's exactly the right answer,
是的，这就是正确的答案，
so this is basically stupid technicality,
所以这是愚蠢的技术细节，
so the virtual addresses are in principle,
所以虚拟地址原则上，
I think 39 bits, right,
我觉得是 39 位，
and but we actually in xv6, only 38 of them,
但是实际上在 xv6 中，只有 38 个，
and as a result, you know the top of the MAXVA for us,
因此，顶端的 MAXVA ，
it is basically the 255 entry.
它是 255 条目。
And the reason we don't use the 39 bits,
我们不使用 39 位的原因是，
is for no particular good reason,
没有特别好的理由，
and then that basically if you have the thirty ninth bit set,
基本上，如果你设置了第 39 位，
then all the remaining bits in the 64 bit address have to be ones.
则 64 位地址中的所有剩余位必须为 1 。
And so we just didn't want to deal with this problem
我们不想处理这个问题，
that if we ever set 39,
如果我们设置了 39 ，
we also have to set the forty forty first, forty second, forty third etc
我们也要设置 40 41 42 43 等，
until the sixty fourth.
直到 64 。
So that's an explanation, that makes sense.
所以这是解释，能理解吗。
Yeah.
嗯。
That's a very good observation though.
这是一个非常好的观察。
So I also had a question about why is the text and data on the same page.
我也有一个问题，为什么文本和数据在同一页上。
Very good question, also.
也是一个很好的问题。
That seems stupid right,
这看起来很愚蠢，
I mean why not put them on separate pages,
我的意思是为什么不把它们放在单独的页面上，
so that you can actually set the permission, that's more carefully.
这样你才能更仔细地设置权限。
And the main reason,
主要原因是，
we're doing that is for simplicity.
我们这样做是为了简单。
Usually make exec more complicated
通常 exec 更复杂，
and we wanted the simplest exec possible.
我们想 exec 尽可能简单。
So a real operating system would not have data and text in the same page,
真正的操作系统不会在同一页中包含数据和文本，
in fact we have to specify
事实上，我们必须指定，
that if you look at the loader flag in the makefile
如果你查看 makefile 中加载器标志，
you'll see that it has the -N option
你会看到，它有 -N 选项，
and that force is actually data and text
它强制数据和文本，
to be in a contiguous not in separate pages.
在一个连续的，而不是在单独的页面中。
Any more questions about this.
关于这个，还有什么问题吗。
I had a follow up question,
我有一个后续问题，
regarding the number of bits, we're using.
关于我们使用的位数。
So you said we're using just 38 bits,
你说我们只用了 38 位，
is it is like the hardware still provides for us to use 39 bits,
硬件仍然提供给我们使用 39 位，
but we are designing our operating system that we're using 38.
但是我们设计操作系统使用 38 位。
Yeah.
嗯。
So we're basically
所以我们，
if the machine had more ram two to thirty eight,
如果机器有超过 2 的 38 次方的内存，
we would not be able to use that ram.
我们就不能用那些内存了。
Now we're running we're assuming
现在我们运行的，我们假设的，
basically much less memory than two to thirty eight,
内存远少于 2 的 38 次方，
so it's not a big deal for us.
所以这对我们来说没什么影响。
But the real operating system, we would have done better.
但是如果是真正的操作系统，我们会做得更好。
So just pure for simplicity.
所以，只是为了简单。
We want to make it as easy for you as possible,
我们想让你尽可能轻松，
by reading a few lines of code possible.
尽可能少阅读代码。
Okay.
好的。
Yeah, makes sense.
是的，理解了。
Okay, so now, let's switch to part two.
好的，那么现在，让我们切换到第二部分。
And so let's bring up, a picture,
让我们来看一张图片，
you probably have looked at a lot.
你可能看了很多次。
The kernel address space right,
内核地址空间，
on the left is virtual address space,
左边是虚拟地址空间，
on the right is physical memory,
右边是物理内存，
you know here are IO devices,
你知道这里是 IO 设备，
and then from here on is you know DRAM,
从这里开始是 DRAM ，
and you know and basically running into what actually one twenty 28 megabytes for us.
直到 128 兆字节。
Because we just assume that
因为我们假设，
there's no more than 250 and one twenty eight megabytes of memory.
内存不超过 250（误） 128 兆字节。
And so this part of the physical memory is the free memory.
所以这部分物理内存就是空闲内存。
And then from that, this was kernel,
从那里开始，这是内核，
oops, I drew a little bit wrong.
哎呀，我画错了。
Let me be more careful,
让我更小心一点，
so, here we basically have kernel text and data.
这里我们有内核文本和数据。
And then you know this memory above, basically memory that the kernel allocator has
然后上面的内存，就是内核分配器拥有的内存，
and from there we allocate memory for user programs,
从那里我们为用户程序分配内存，
we allocate memory for pagetables, etc.
我们为页表等分配内存。
Kernel allocates everything for them,
内核为它们分配所有，
until it runs out of memory,
直到内存耗尽，
when it runs out it gets to one twenty eight megabyte
当它用完时，它会达到 128 兆字节，
and then it starts returning errors or system calls.
然后它开始返回错误或系统调用。
Okay.
好的。
Good, so let me pull off my first part correct,
好的，那么让我把第一部分做好，
in some sense of this assignment it was part two of the assignment,
从某种意义上说，这是任务的第二部分，
was just to run with or copy the kernel pagetables,
就是运行或者复制内核页表，
and every process has its own kernel pagetables.
而且每个进程都有自己的内核页表。
That was basically that's the assignment here,
这就是这里的任务，
so let me for jumping into the code,
所以让我进入代码，
let me actually see a couple things,
让我实际看几件事，
more general things about it.
关于它的，更一般的事情。
So part two.
所以第二部分。
And maybe the first question really to sort of get your head around is
也许你头脑中的第一个问题是，
like you know in some ways you do something trivial right,
在某些方面你做了一些微不足道的事，
we already have the kernel pagetable,
我们已经有了内核页表，
we just have to make [] copies of it,
我们只需复制[]个副本，
for one copy for each particular process.
每个进程一个副本。
You, you might say well you know how hard can it be,
你可能会说，这能有多难，
it turns out it was a little bit harder for a couple reasons.
因为几个原因，这是有些难度的。
Some good ones, some less good ones,
一些好的原因，一些不太好的原因，
harder than it seems.
它比看起来要难。
And one reason is that
一个原因是，
you know xv6 code it's specialized,
xv6 代码很特别，
for one kernel pagetable.
针对一个内核页表。
You know, you saw that in kvminit.
你在 kvminit 中看到的。
Yeah, and so that makes it a little bit generalizing,
是的，所以这就有点一概而论，
you know it's a little bit of work,
你知道这需要一些工作，
because you have to modify the xv6 code.
因为你必须修改 xv6 代码。
kvminit as you also saw is not the full,
如你所见， kvminit 不是完全，
for building pagetable for the kernel.
为内核构建页表。
There's also stuff in procinit,
也有一些在 procinit 中，
that actually adds mappings to the kernel pagetable.
它添加映射到内核页表。
And there's even something in virtio_disk,
甚至有一些在 virtio_disk 。
the actually interacts, you know the kernel pagetable.
真正与内核页表进行交互。
So basically there's no one single place in the kernel,
所以内核中没有唯一的地方，
where actually the kernel pagetable actually is built.
用于构建内核页表。
Then the third reason, why you know this is slightly complicated,
第三个原因，为什么这有些复杂，
because you also have to deal with cleanup.
因为你还得做清理工作。
So there's the aspect of actually creating these copies,
因为有一个创建这些副本的方面，
but when every time user process exit,
所以每次用户进程退出时，
we also have to clean up those pagetables that were in use,
我们还要清理那些使用过的页表，
because we want to return them to the pool of free memory,
因为我们希望将它们放回到空闲内存池中，
so that we can use them later,
好让我们以后可以使用它们，
so that we can keep on running processes.
以便我们可以继续运行进程。
That's what happens there.
这就是那里发生的事情。
And that makes things a little bit complicated,
这让事情变得有些复杂，
because we've got to be little careful,
因为我们必须要小心，
in actually freeing the kernel pagetable
在释放内核页表
or copy of the kernel pagetable,
或内核页表的副本时，
but we certainly don't want to,
我们当然不想
you know, free memory that actually still in use,
释放仍在使用中的内存，
or page table entries are still used by other pagetables.
或别的页表仍在使用的页表条目。
So we gotta be careful there,
所以我们得小心，
and then, you know basically, it's easy to make a small error.
然后，你知道，很容易出现错误。
You know pagetable, when your copy those pagetables.
当你复制那些页表时。
You know if you get a little thing,
如果你[得到]一点东西，
you know basically you get a hard hard bug.
你会得到一个很难的 bug 。
And one of the problems here is I said earlier is,
这里的一个问题是，我之前说过，
the hard bug shows up much much later.
困难的 bug 出现的时间要晚得多。
You've built the kernel pagetable,
你已经构建了内核页表，
are built copy of the kernel pagetable,
构建了内核页表的副本，
all looks fine, you load loaded in satp,
一切看起来都很好，你装入 satp 寄存器，
they may even maybe the kernel runs for a little while, and then panics.
甚至内核会运行一小段时间，然后才死机。
And it turns out you know the reason that panics,
结果发现死机的原因，
because you made some small mistake in the pagetable,
因为你在页表中犯了个小错误，
long, long time ago.
在很久很久以前。
And so this is one reason why
所以这就是为什么
it makes you know makes life difficult for kernel programming.
它会让内核编程很困难。
And you know and basically these hard bugs,
你知道，这些困难的 bug ，
basically are just time consuming to track down.
基本上都很费时间去追踪。
Because of the point that you know happens,
因为发生的时候，
that's actually not the real cause of of the bug,
其实不是 bug 的真正原因，
but about you know the real cause,
但是真正的原因，
you know somewhere way earlier when you set up the pagetables.
是你之前设置页表时的某个地方。
Okay, um.
好的。
So it turns out,
所以结果是，
there are two approaches to go about it,
有两种方法解决这个问题，
you know to this lab which sort of two solution approaches.
你知道，这个实验可以采用两种解决方案。
In fact, some of you have probably used a mixture of them,
事实上，你们中的一些人可能混合使用它们，
the one you know approach what call copy approach.
第一个方法是 copy 方法。
And the copy approach basically literally makes a copy to the kernel pagetable,
copy 方法从字面上复制内核页表，
so every time you need a new kernel pagetable,
所以每次你都需要一个新的内核页表，
you allocate pages for the pagetable,
你为页表分配页面，
you fill them in etc, etc.
你为它们填充数据，等等。
And there's, that's one approach, the second approach is
还有一种方法，第二种方法是，
basically to share the kernel pagetable,
共享内核页表，
and in this case, what you do is
在这种情况下，你要做的是
instead of trying to make a literally nice clean copy of the kernel pagetables,
不是创建一个内核页表的干净副本，
you share all the entries that are basically are going to be unmodified.
而是共享不会修改的所有条目。
You know from the assignment,
你从任务中知道，
that basically anything above CLINT to PLIC address,
基本上从 CLINT 到 PLIC 地址以上的任何内容，
is actually going to be unchanged, unmodified,
实际上是不变的，
there's nothing you have to load there.
那里没有你要加载的东西。
In the part three,
在第三部分，
so you know what are basically,
你知道，基本上，
all the entries from above zero are probably identical,
从零开始的所有条目可能是相同的，
so you could share those entries, if you will.
所以你可以分享这些条目。
So that both approaches are actually perfectly fine.
这两种方法都很好。
It's not abundantly clear, which one is the better one.
没有明确的，哪一个更好。
My solution, take this approach.
我的解决方案，采取这种方法（共享方法）。
And I don't really have great justification for it
我没有很好的理由，
other than maybe partially laziness.
除了可能部分原因是可以偷懒。
I didn't want to think too hard,
我不想想太多，
what's in the kernel pagetable,
内核页表中有什么，
and so I figured out all the things that are going to stay the same,
所以我想出所有东西保持不变，
why do you copy them over
为什么复制它们，
or you know copy the ptes over
或者复制 pte ，
and then I have to think too hard about
然后我不得不认真考虑，
actually isn't that part of the kernel address space.
这实际上不是内核地址空间的一部分。
And you know leads to short code,
这会导致更少代码，
but you know I'm not sure actually
但是我不确定，
shorter than, for example, the copy solution.
比复制解决方案更少。
But it's important to realize that basically
但重要的是要认识到，
there are two different ways of going about this particular problem.
有两种不同的方法来解决这个特定问题。
In either case, you know whatever approach you use,
在这两种情况下，无论你用什么方法，
you know there's sort of an implementation strategy to it.
都有某种实施策略。
And you know the implementation strategy that I use
你知道我使用的实施策略，
for almost any kernel program
对于几乎任何内核程序，
is to do everything in baby steps.
都是按部就班地做所有事情。
So I might have, for general plan in my head
所以我可能，在我的脑海里有一个总的计划，
about how I go over the whole,
关于我是如何从头走到尾的，
you know all the changes I want to make,
我要做的所有改变，
but once I start making these changes,
但是一旦我开始做这些改变，
I do like one or two,
我先做一两个，
and then make sure that those work first
然后确保它们起作用，
and then you know, keep going,
然后继续往前走，
and the other thing I do
我做的另一件事是，
is mostly used as a strategy to keep the existing code,
主要是保留现有代码，
don't really modify certainly not initially,
不是修改最初的代码，
I just add code and switch to this new code
我是添加代码，并切换到新代码，
and then the little baby steps
然后[按部就班]，
and the reason I'm doing that is
我这么做的原因是，
that I can easily compare old new code,
我可以很容易地比较新旧代码，
and I always have a working old solution,
我总是有一个有效的旧解决方案，
that I can just roll back to,
我可以直接回到过去，
so in case some strange bugs happens,
如果发生了一些奇怪的错误，
then I can go back maybe one step and then try again,
然后我可以后退一步，然后再试一次，
so you figure out like I said were my reason was wrong.
所以就像我说的，那样知道我的推理是错的。
Basically you know baby steps what partly
小步走，部分原因是，
because these bugs are so hard to track down.
这些 bug 太难追踪了。
Okay, let me switch to code,
好的，让我切换到代码，
so maybe starting vm.c.
从 vm.c 开始。
So, the, here's the existing kvminit,
这是现有的 kvminit ，
and actually can everybody see the code?
每个人都可以看到代码吗？
Okay, and, the assignment we are asked
好的，任务要求我们
for correct is to make a copy of it
对它（内核页表）做一个副本，
and the way I do that is,
我做的方式是，
let me see where that is.
让我看看在哪里。
So here's my uvmcreate,
这是我的 uvmcreate ，
that's just boring part,
那只是无聊的部分，
that's basically creating, allocating the top level page directory,
基本上就是创建分配顶级页目录，
also the l2 page directory.
还有 l2 页目录。
And then here's my kvm,
然后这里是我的 kvm- ，
the equivalent of kvminit.
相当于 kvminit 。
So I get the top of the page directory here,
我在这里获得了顶部的页目录，
in this site.
在这个位置。
Then, basically I copy the top 511 entries from the kernel pagetable
然后，我会复制从内核页表前 511 个条目，
that was already set up by kvminit,
它已经由 kvminit 设置好，
and so that gives me most of the kernel pagetable.
这给了我大部分的内核页表。
And then, I just have to map in all the devices
然后，我需要映射所有设备，
that live in the zero entry,
它们在这里 0 号条目。
because zero entry, the entry that we're going to modify it later
因为 0 号条目，我们稍后要修改它，
or we're going to map user pages into the bottom.
或者我们会将用户页面映射到底部。
And there's a couple devices that live in that in zero entry,
有几个设备在 0 号条目中，
those you know device needs to be added to the to this,
那些的设备需要添加到，
per process pagetable, kernel page table.
每个进程的内核页表。
And so maybe I go back to this picture earlier.
所以我回到前面的这张图片上。
So let me put up the kernel pagetable again,
让我再次设置内核页表，
maybe this picture as good as any,
可能这张图片跟任何都一样，
so if you think about my solution,
所以如果你考虑我的解决方案，
basically these entries I just share with existing kernel pagetable,
基本上这些条目我只是与现有内核页表共享，
so I don't have to allocate any l1 or l2 or l0 levels,
所以我不需要分配任何 l1 或 l2 或 l0 级别，
they already exists
它们已经存在了，
and the only thing I do is basically literally copy pte entry.
我唯一做的就是字面意思上的复制 pte 条目。
So only the bottom part or the bottom entry that is the piece,
所以只有底部部分或底部条目，
I need to actually rebuild or copy explicitly instead of copying ptes.
我需要真正重建或复制，而不只是复制 pte 。
And that covers you know the bottom one gigabyte address space.
这就覆盖了底部的 1G 字节的地址空间。
In one page covers 4096.
在一页中包含 4096 。
And so this you know this entry covers five twelve.
所以这个条目包含 512 。
But this has been two megabyte.
这（最右边的）是 2 兆字节了。
And this is one gigabyte
而这（中间的）是一千兆字节，
and basically only one of these entries, I need to fill it.
所以只有一个条目，我需要填充它。
That makes sense?
能理解吗?
So returning to my code and basically,
回到我的代码，基本上，
that's all I do, kvmcreate.
这就是我所做的一切， kvmcreate 。
And in kv- my kvmfree is maybe not, maybe clean solution,
在我的 kvmfree 中是清理方案，
but I take full advantage of the knowledge
但我充分利用了这些知识，
that I don't have to do anything from the entries one to 511
我不需要对条目 1 到 511 做任何事情，
in the top page level directory.
在顶级页目录中。
The only entry to do anything about is
唯一要处理的条目是
the bottom entry of the kernel of the top level directory.
内核顶级目录的底部条目。
That points to one l1 entry
它指向一个 l1 条目，
and that one l1 entry, I just need to go through
那个 l1 条目，我只需要遍历，
and free old l2 or l0 entries.
释放旧的 l2 或 l0 条目。
And then the ends you know free l1
然后，释放 l1 ，
and then the kernel pagetable.
然后是内核页表。
And so that's my k- kvmfree and my kvmcreate.
这就是我的 kvmfree 和 kvmcreate 。
So that allows me to create a kernel pagetable process
这样我就可以创建内核页表进程，
and then free once is when we're done.
然后在使用完成后释放。
Sorry, quick question.
抱歉，提个小问题。
Could you explain again,
您能再解释一下，
the reasoning for only using one to five twelve and not zero?
为什么只使用 1 到 512 而不使用 0 ？
Yes.
是。
Okay, so,
好的，那么，
maybe the easy thing to do actually let me go back through the picture here.
也许最容易的是，让我回到这里的图片。
So we have a kernel address space, correct.
所以我们有一个内核地址空间。
And you know this O x eight zero zero zero zero blah blah blah,
这个 Ox8000 等等，
in, um.
在，嗯。
What entry does O x zero fall into in the for the top level page directory.
在顶层页面目录中， Ox0 属于哪个条目。
It's like, the.
比如。
Zeroth entry?
0 号条目？
No, not to zeroth entry, right.
不，不是 0 号条目。
So whatever you know what zero entry like this entry,
所以你知道 0 号条目，
how much does it cover this entry.
这个条目包含多少？
How much address space,
多少地址空间，
does this bottom entry of the zero entry of the top level page directory cover.
顶层页面目录的底部条目即 0 号条目包含多少。
I think CLINT is,
我认为 CLINT 是
it's free between zero and 0x2000.
在 0 到 0x2000 之间。
Yeah, so okay so maybe I'm going to,
是的，也许我会这么做，
I think you're absolutely right direction,
我认为你的方向是正确的，
so the bottom entry copy one gigabyte, right.
所以最下面的条目复制了一千兆字节。
And we know like maybe I can.
我们知道，也许我可以。
We saw the bottom entry one gigabyte which,
我们看到最下面的条目是一千兆字节，
in that one gigabyte just CLINT the PLIC, right,
在那一千兆字节有 CLINT 和 PLIC ，
UART and VIRTIO_disk, I believe.
我相信还有 UART 和 VIRTIO_disk 。
And then KERNBASE actually already sits up in a higher entry, right.
然后 KERNBASE 位于一个更高的条目上。
We can compute if we wanted to,
我们可以计算一下，
we could take 0x eight zero correct,
我们可以取 0x80- ，
shifted twelve, shift nine, shift nine,
移位 12 ，移位 9 ，移位 9 ，
and I I think I don't remember the top we have what is.
我想，我不记得顶部是什么了。
Try to figure it out, if you want to actually maybe we'll try.
试着弄清楚，也许我们来试一试。
This is always very risky to do in lecture,
在演讲中这样做总是有[风险]的，
but, so, gdb.
所以， gdb 。
So let's go to layout, here's KERNBASE,
我们来看看 memlayout.h ，这是 KERNBASE ，
so we could print.
所以我们可以打印。
So shift is twelve, that gives us, that offset.
移位是 12 ，这给了我们，偏移量。
Oops.
哎呀。
Good as that, so then we'll shift that guy.
好的，然后我们移位这个值。
I think you could see this.
我想你可以看到这个。
Nine.
九。
Right now is the next entry one more,
现在再做一次，
so this entry two.
所以这是条目 2 。
Does it make sense.
能理解吗。
So we go back to our picture here.
所以我们回到这里来看图片。
Basically KERNBASE is entry two,
KERNBASE 是条目 2 ，
in the top of page directory, right.
在顶级页目录中。
So and we know from the third part of the assignment,
我们从作业的第三部分了解到，
basically we don't really have to worry about anything above PLIC.
我们不需要考虑 PLIC 上面的任何东西。
And all that stuff falls actually entry zero.
所有这些东西上都在条目 0 。
Okay?
好的?
So that answer the earlier question.
所以这回答了之前的问题。
Yes, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, so now we the only thing we have left to do is,
好的，现在我们要做的还剩下的就是，
you know, double check where we got to call this function kvmcreate,
再次检查调用函数 kvmcreate 的地方，
and and you know that's going to be allocproc.
这将是 allocproc 。
So, and.
所以，并且。
Oops.
哎呀。
Here where is the new process initialized,
这里是新进程初始化的地方，
then you know I'm sure all of you is exactly the same way,
我相信你们都是一样的，
you entry, you allocate when you declare field in the proc structure
当你在 proc 结构中声明字段时，
and basically the result of it is actually what we stick in the kernel pagetable.
它的结果，我们放在内核页表中。
Okay, then we only the thing that we have to worry about,
好的，我们需要考虑的另一件事是，
of course we need to use the pagetable,
当然我们需要使用页表，
and so we need to look at the scheduler.
所以，我们需要查看调度器。
Basically, the assignment more or less told you what to do
基本上，任务多少会告诉你做什么，
which is you know before you switch to that user process,
在切换到用户进程之前，
you need to switch the kernel pagetables,
你需要切换内核页表，
which basically means loading, you know, this process kernel pagetable in satp.
意味着加载进程内核页表到 satp 。
And then when you're done switching in running the other process,
然后当你完成切换来运行另一个进程，
you come back from running the other process
你从另一个进程返回，
and you're gonna go back and run the scheduler,
然后你回到并运行调度程序，
you gotta switch back to the main kernel pagetable,
你必须切换回主内核页表，
the [] kernel pagetable,
[]内核页表，
because that's the one that actually used by scheduler.
因为这才是调度器实际使用的。
And why do we need to do this switch,
为什么我们做这个切换，
why is this important.
为什么这很重要。
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
So it picks the right kernel pagetable,
因为它选择了正确的内核页表，
because the satp, when you go to the pagetable entries,
因为 satp ，当你转到页表条目时，
it picks the right,
它选择了，
it picks the right pagetable to pick from.
它选择了正确的页表。
Yeah, hold on or something more than a second.
嗯，稍等一下。
Yeah, so okay, so when we stop.
是的，所以好的，当我们停下来的时候。
Okay, let me another way to ask this question,
好的，让我换一种方式问这个问题，
when is this kernel pagetable freed.
这个内核页表是什么时候释放的。
When the user process is done,
当用户进程完成时，
so if we didn't switch,
所以如果我们不交换（页表），
that would mean that that,
那就意味着，
we could be using a pagetable of a process that was being freed,
我们可以使用一个被释放进程的页表，
so the pagetable was freed,
页表被释放了，
so we don't want to be dependent on the process were not running right now.
所以，我们不想依赖于当前未运行的进程。
Yeah, exactly, we can never free the page table of the process that's currently running.
没错，我们永远不能释放当前正在运行的进程的页表。
So we have to have some plan,
所以我们要有一个计划，
you know to actually free process at the point that they're not running anymore.
在进程不再运行时释放它们。
And you know the wait system call is our way out,
wait 系统调用是我们的退出方式，
basically wait calls look if there's any children
wait 系统调用查看有没有子进程，
that are are not you know that can be cleaned up.
决定是不是可以清理。
And then they cleans them up.
然后把它们清理掉。
And that means that basically,
也就是说，
when the parent process switch over process,
当父进程切换进程时，
we're going to make absolutely sure that you know that,
我们必须保证，
the pagetable that is loaded in the satp register,
satp 寄存器中加载的页表，
is not you know one of the,
不是，
is not that process you know pagetable will actually currently free.
不是那个将要释放的进程页表。
You know it could be the case there's no process running at all right
也可能根本没有进程在运行，
and so the scheduler basically has its own pagetable,
所以调度器有它自己的页表，
sort of all processes can actually be cleaned up.
所以，所有进程都可以被清理。
That makes sense?
能理解吗？
I'm sorry, I had a question,
抱歉，我有个问题，
is it that you're mapping the C L I N T
你是不是把 CLINT 映射到
into the new process kernel pagetables?
新的进程内核页表中了？
Why?
为什么？
Because I think the assignment says like I only have to,
因为任务说的我只需要，
user process, you will not be bigger than CLINT is that it.
用户进程不会比 CLINT 更大，好像是的。
When I map both the PLIC and the CLINT, right,
当我映射 PLIC 和 CLINT 时，
and so but I think the assignment told us that,
我认为任务告诉我们，
so what is the lowest one.
什么是最低的那个。
I think there PLIC is the lowest one,
我想 PLIC 是最低的那个，
and this [] told us,
这告诉我们，
that the user process will not be bigger than the PLIC address.
用户进程不会大于 PLIC 地址。
Okay.
好的。
Just to make it easy,
只是为了简单，
we could then,
我们可以，
want to make it as easy as possible for you
想让它对你来说尽可能简单，
clear you could have done a better if you wanted to.
当然，你愿意的话，可以做得更好。
But you know that was the simplest thing to do.
但是，你知道这是最简单的事情。
So you have to make a few modifications to get it to work.
所以，你需要做一些修改才能让它正常工作。
Any further questions?
还有什么问题吗？
I have a question,
我有一个问题，
is it possible that you can copy zero to five twelve
能不能复制 0 到 512 ，
and then every time you switch,
然后每次切换时，
so you're still using like the global root pagetable
仍在使用，比如全局根页表，
except you only copy the first root page table,
除了复制第一个根页表，
and every time you switch a process,
每次切换进程时，
you copy over the user's addresses over to.
都复制用户地址到。
Yeah.
是的。
Is that possible to do.
能不能这么做。
In principle I think you could do something like that,
理论上，我认为你可以这样做，
so instead of basically doing when you allocate a process and free it,
所以，不是分配一个进程，再释放它，
you could do to dynamically during this scheduler switch.
你可以在调度程序切换期间动态执行。
Um, seems complicated.
嗯，看起来很复杂。
That might be more costly,
那可能花费更多，
because that means that every time you switch between two processes,
因为，这意味着每次在两个进程之间切换时，
you may have to make a copy of parts of the kernel pagetable.
你可能必须复制内核页表的一部分。
And so that might be turn to perform,
所以这可能对性能有影响，
it's not an ideal thing.
不是一件理想的事情。
The assignment didn't really say anything about it,
任务没有说任何关于它的事，
you might have timed out in usertests, if you did that.
如果你这样做了，它可能在 usertests 中超时。
Yeah I was just wondering,
是的，我只是想知道，
because I tried that approach,
因为我试过那个方法，
and it was a bad experience,
这是一次糟糕的经历，
I was wondering if that was possible.
我想知道这是否可行。
I can imagine, but I I think it's in principle possible,
我可以想象的到，但是我认为理论上是可行的，
you could allocate a new page table correctly and switch every time,
你可以每次分配新的页表并切换，
and free it when you switch out.
并在切换出来的时候释放它。
I don't think it's simple,
我不认为这很简单，
but you know in principle it's possible I think.
但是，你知道，我认为理论上是可行的。
Perhaps some other modifications to xv6.
可能对 xv6 做一些其他修改。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Of course the other change that,
当然另一个改变是，
of course have to make is usertrapret,
必须要改的是 usertrapret ，
you got to make sure that
你必须确保，
actually you run with the the processes kernel page table.
你使用进程内核页表运行。{}进程内核页表。
Okay?
好的？
Okay, so let's switch them to,
好的，那我们切换到，
I guess part three.
第三部分。
To switch back to actually here.
切换回这里。
Okay, so,
好的，那么，
actually that's maybe not a helpful picture.
这可能不是一张有帮助的图片。
Okay, part three.
好的，第三部分。
So basically what our plan is,
所以基本上我们的计划是，
we have our kernel pagetable as before,
我们有像之前一样的内核页表，
and you know we have the PLIC entry sitting somewhere.
我们有 PLIC 条目在某个地方。
And what we're gonna do is,
我们要做的是，
we're gonna use you know everything below PLIC,
我们将使用 PLIC 下面的所有东西，
to actually store the user pagetable,
来保存用户页表，
we're going to map the user pagetable into all the user program,
我们将把用户页表映射到所有的用户程序中，
the user program actually in the kernel pagetable,
用户程序实际上在内核页表中，
in the bottom.
在底部。
And that's the goal,
这就是我们的目标，
and what's the first question to ask,
第一个要问的问题是，
you know why the [] do that.
为什么[]要这么做。
Is there any you know any advantage of it
这样有什么好处吗，
and you know I think maybe the,
我觉得可能，
it may be a easy way
这可能是一种简单的方式
to see why it might be interesting
来理解为什么它很有趣，
is to [] compare to copyin.
是[]与 copyin 比较。
The new copyin and the old copyin.
新 copyin 和旧 copyin 。
So, if you know what happens in the copyin,
所以，如果， copyin 发生了什么，
it correctly, copyin copies data from the user space into the kernel address space.
copyin 将数据从用户空间复制到内核地址空间。
Um, and but you know if the kernel has does not have the user address map,
但是如果内核没有用户地址映射。
basically the kernel has to do this page the time, correct,
内核必须在这时分配这个页，
because the pages in virtual address space may be continuous
因为虚拟地址空间中的页面可以是连续的，
with the physical address space, they're not continuous.
尽管对于物理地址空间，它们不是连续的。
And basically with the kernel does in copyin,
内核在 copyin 上所做的，
it basically translates the virtual user address into physical address.
将虚拟用户地址转换为物理地址。
Since the kernel has all physical memory mapped with identity mapping,
由于内核具有所有物理内存映射，
the physical address is also a valid kernel virtual address
物理地址[也是]有效的内核虚拟地址，
and then it basically moves whatever part of that page,
然后它移动那一页的部分，
physical page needs to be copied that actually copies it.
那些需要复制的物理页。
And so if data structure,
如果某个数据结构，
for example spans, you know, two page boundary,
跨越两个个页面边界，
like for example, the sysinfo struct may be used in lab two,
比如，在实验 2 中使用的 sysinfo 结构，
maybe spans a pagetable boundary,
可能跨越页表边界，
it will copy like maybe you know
它会复制，比如可能是，
some bytes from the first physical page
第一个物理页的一些字节，
and then some bytes from the second physical page.
然后是第二物理页的一些字节。
Does it make sense.
这个能理解吗。
That's what the kernel copyin does,
这就是内核 copyin 所做的，
and the goal was basically to get them into a new copyin,
目标是让它们使用新的 copyin ，
where the kernel program didn't really have to worry about the physical layout,
使内核程序不必担心物理布局，
basically off the user address space.
不占用用户地址空间。
And this new copyin,
这个新 copyin ，
you know we see we basically do nothing,
我们可以看到基本上什么都不做，
literally nothing else, just copy,
没有其他东西，只是复制，
do, you know, from the user addresses straight into the kernel.
从用户地址直接到内核。
And we don't really have to call walk anymore,
而且我们也不再需要调用 walk 了，
because we can rely on the,
因为我们可以依赖，
we set up that the pagetables correctly,
我们正确设置页表，
now the pagetable hardware will do the walk for us.
现在，页表硬件将为我们做 walk 。
Right.
是的。
And so that was the goal,
这就是我们的目标，
and so that makes life of kernel programmers are a little bit easier,
所以这让内核程序员的生活更轻松一点，
on any other advantages to this approach.
这种方法还有没有别的优点。
Is it also more performance,
是不是性能也更好，
because the hardware is gonna do the walking and not software.
因为硬件来做 walk 而不是软件。
Yeah, one way to,
是啊，一个方法，
I think their performance implications for sure,
我认为肯定有性能的提高，
one way to think about this is that
考虑这个的一种方式是，
in copyin correct, if the kernel data structure
在 copyin 中，如果内核数据结构
or data data that we copied from user space to kernel spaces big,
或者我们从用户空间复制到内核空间的数据比较大，
we have to do that you know page at a time, right,
我们必须这样做，一次一页，
in every page, we have to call this function walkaddr,
在每个页面中，我们都必须调用函数 walkaddr ，
and then there's the internal walking.
然后是内部的 walk 。
And so, this might actually be a reasonable expenses expensive.
所以，这可能是一个昂贵的花费。
What examples are there examples of
有什么例子，
where the kernel copies a lot of data from user space.
是内核从用户空间复制大量数据。
Which system call might copy a ton of data from user space.
哪个系统调用可能会从用户空间复制大量数据。
Write?
write?
Yeah write, write, you're right,
是的， write ，你说得对，
you can give an arbitrary, an arbitrary buffer of arbitrary size.
你可以给出任意大小的任意缓冲区。
And you know the kernel [] may have to copy this into,
内核可能将其复制到，
for example, the file system or into a pipe.
文件系统或管道中。或者放进管子里。
And that could be a reasonable expensive.
这是很昂贵的。
You gotta think what is another advantage,
你想想还有什么好处，
if the user,
如果用户，
we didn't explore that in this assignment,
我们在任务中没有研究这个，
we should we could have one another advantage.
应该还有别的优点。
So if you think about,
所以如果你想一想，
some of these, this code here correct,
这里的其中一些代码，
when it takes a structure out of user space,
当它把结构移出用户空间，
it copies the whole structure into kernel space.
它将整个结构复制到内核空间。
If user space is mapped into the kernel pagetable,
如果用户空间被映射到内核页表，
do we have to do that.
我们也一定要这么做吗。
For example, if we have to update one field of the structure.
比如，如果我们需要更新结构体中的一个字段。
So if data structure is just mapped into the kernel address space right,
如果数据结构只是映射到内核地址空间，
then we can usually read and write,
那么我们可以读写，
you know with store instruction through that particular data structure,
通过 store 指令到特定的数据结构，
we can use update one field.
我们可以更新一个字段。
Unlike the kernel now does,
与现在内核做的不同，
basically it copies the structure from kernel space to user space,
它将结构体从内核空间复制到用户空间，
and then maybe back out using copyout.
然后可能再使用 copyout 退出。
And so we map the user space into,
因此，我们将用户空间映射到，
the user program into the kernel address space,
将用户程序映射到内核地址空间，
we can just manipulate it much more freely
我们可以更自由地操纵它，
than the way we do it now.
而不是我们现在的做法。
Does that make sense,
这能理解吗？
in terms of motivation, why many kernels actually have this particular structure
就动机而言，为什么许多内核都有这种特殊的结构，
where they map bottom part of the user,
映射底部是用户，
were to map the user program into the bottom part of the kernel address space.
将用户程序映射到内核地址空间的底部。
Okay?
好的？
Okay, so so let's see, look at my code
好的，让我们看我的代码，
and and so you understand what actually.
好让你明白实际是什么。
I I guess so there's basically one function, that is the key,
我想有一个函数是关键，
you know assume we were building somewhere valid user pagetable,
假设我们正在建立有效的用户页表 ，
and then we just have to
然后我们需要将
map entries from the user pagetable into the kernel pagetable,
条目从用户页表映射到内核页表，
the processes kernel pagetables,
进程内核页表，
that function kvmmapuser exactly does this.
函数 kvmmapuser 就是这样做的。
And it's pretty boring,
这挺枯燥的，
the main couple interesting points to point out in work,
工作中主要的几个点是，
yeah yeah that's the same sort of interfaces to uvmalloc whatever
是的，那是与 uvmalloc 同样类型的接口，
or basically if you know
或者如果，
you go from the old size up to the new size page at a time.
你从旧尺寸页面转到新尺寸页面。
Yeah.
嗯。
You find the upte,
你找到 upte ，
you know the pointer to the pte for that particular virtual address
指向特定虚拟地址的 pte 的指针，
in the user page table.
在用户页表中。
And so we look at the,
所以我们来看一下，
if you look at the picture
如果你看这张图片，
that we had a little while back,
我们有一段时间了，
you know look at this picture.
看这张图片。
Basically, what this is going to return correct is,
这将返回的是，
we're going to walk the user pagetable
我们遍历用户页表，
and we'll find for example the upte
我们找到 upte ，
that maps in that particular virtual address
它映射到特定虚拟地址，
where we basically pointer to that entry into the pagetable,
那个地址指向页表中的那个条目。
and that's what walk does.
这就是 walk 所做的。
And so if thing is mapped, it's not
如果这个东西映射了，它不是零，
that must mean at least the answer is
那一定意味着，至少答案是，
just to check, double check that actually the map is there.
检查映射是否在那里。
We check this valid,
我们检查这是有效的，
there's debugging help in some sense,
这在某种意义上有帮助调试，
you know we should be the case that is valid.
你知道我们应该在有效的情况下。
And then I do the same thing in the kernel pagetable,
然后我在内核页表中做同样的事情，
I look up that virtual address also in the process of kernel pagetable,
我还查看进程内核页表中的虚拟地址，
but I call this time walk with one,
但这一次我调用 walk 带上 1 ，
so it actually allocates intermediate pages if necessary.
因此，如果需要，它会分配中间页。
Then once I got the pointer to the kernel pte,
然后，我得到指向内核 pte 的指针，
I just copy the user pte into the kernel pte.
我只是将用户 pte 复制到内核 pte 。
So probably a lot of you called mappages.
可能你们中的很多人调用了 mappages 。
But I just copied directly the pte into the kernel pte
但我是直接将 pte 复制到内核 pte 中，
and of course I gotta disable some bits
当然，我要禁用一些位，
which we'll talk about in a second,
稍后我们会讲到，
but, the essence of it is,
但是，它的实质是，
I just copy the kernel page pte entries.
我只是复制内核页面 pte 条目。
And so that means that,
这意味着，
for example the physical memory for the user program is shared,
用户程序的物理内存是共享的，
between kernel space and user space.
在内核空间和用户空间之间。
Okay, does that make sense.
好的，能理解吗。
Okay, so in terms of switching up some bits
好的，切换一些位，
a little bit more than necessary,
比需要的多一点，
but I switch off the execute bit,
我关闭了执行位，
I I switch off the write bit,
我关闭了写入位，
is copyin only needs to read never writes to it
因为 copyin 只需要读取，不需要写入，
or copyout does that.
copyout 也是这样。
And then, you have to switch up u bit.
然后，你也必须切换 u 标志位。
And that is a sort of RISC-V specific thing,
这是一种 RISC-V 特定的东西，
that if you're running in kernel mode,
如果你在内核模式下运行，
and you've been u bit is set in the pte entry,
并且你在 pte 条目中设置了 u 标志位，
the kernel can actually not access that particular page.
内核就不能访问那个特定页面。
In fact you can,
事实上，你可以，
this is almost a choice,
这是一个选择，
you can also actually program the RISC-V hardware,
你还可以对 RISC-V 硬件进行编程，
that basically in kernel mode and ignores the u bit.
这处于内核模式，并忽略 u 标志位。
And um, but xv6 doesn't do that,
但是 xv6 没有做这一点，
so you have to switch up the u bit.
所以你必须切换 u 标志位。
Any questions about the u bit,
有关于 u 标志位的问题吗，
because the required number of you asked about it.
因为有很多人人问到了它。
So is this done just to make sure
那么这么做只是为了确保，
that the kernel doesn't do anything bad to user memory.
内核不会对用户内存做什么坏事。
Yeah, so why is this the case why is this,
是的，那么为什么会这样？
you know, so the question is like is this for debugging reasons,
所以问题是，这是出于调试的原因，
or is there sort of isolation reasons to do so.
还是有某种隔离的原因这样做。
And, I think this is mostly for debugging reasons.
我想这主要是出于调试的原因。
Because the kernel is in full control anyway, right,
因为内核反正是完全控制的，
kernel can change the satp register,
内核可以修改 satp 寄存器，
as well it can disable paging as it wants to,
它页可以禁用分页，
so it's not like you know the user space is protected from the kernel,
所以不是，保护用户空间不受内核影响，
I think it's mostly to basically help kernel development,
我认为主要是为了帮助内核开发，
for example xv6 case correct,
从 xv6 来说，
unmodified xv6 should never be reference user page period.
未修改的 xv6 不应该引用用户页面。
Um, and um, and so that you know,
还有，你知道，
and basically this just helps if you happen to do
如果你这样做，会有所帮助，
that by accident anyway you would get immediately page fault
出现意外，你会立即得到页面错误，
and you know a kernel panic
内核错误，
and it will help the kernel debug,
这将有助于内核调试，
developer to debug the kernel.
开发人员调试内核。
Does that makes sense.
能理解吗。
Yeah, thank you.
是的，谢谢。
I have a follow up question to that,
我有一个后续的问题，
I think the part about the user bit makes sense,
我理解了关于用户位的部分，
but what about the write and execute bits.
但是关于写入和执行位是怎样的？
Yeah.
是的。
So does the execute bit have to be on?
执行位必须打开吗？
What does the kernel do with this page?
内核用这个页面做什么？
The only read from, right,
它只是读，
the only thing the only instruction
唯一的事情，唯一的指令，
that basically grabs data from this pages,
是从这个页面获取数据，
memmove instruction and copyin.
memmove 指令和 copyin 。
So it only it does execute load instructions from it,
所以它只执行加载指令，
or loads values from that particular page
或者从特定页面加载值，
and the page should only contain data.
并且页面应该只包含数据。
And so there's no reason that the kernel should be writing to that page
所以内核没有理由写入该页，
and so it has to be conservative,
所以出于保守考虑，
I disabled the write bit.
我禁用了写入位。
And there should be confirmed never executed instruction from that page,
并且不应该从该页面执行指令，
so I disable the execute bit too.
所以我也禁用了执行位。
Again, this is mostly I think for debugging reasons,
再说一次，我认为这主要是出于调试的原因，
not for isolation reasons.
而不是因为隔离的原因。
OK, makes sense, thanks.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
Okay, so now the only thing we need to do,
好的，那么现在我们唯一需要做的是，
is basically there's a bunch of places
基本上有一些位置，
where this code is being where this function is being called.
这个代码，这个调用函数在什么位置。
And we need to look at these places where call
我们看看这些调用的位置，
to understand what's going on,
了解发生了什么，
or how to use,
或者怎么使用，
and I think maybe one of the interesting ones
我想其中一个有趣的是，
that you know numbers of you asked about
你们中很少人问到，
is fork.
就是 fork 。
And exactly we talk about both of them.
确切地说，我们讨论他们两个。
The first fork,
第一个 fork ，
so here's call to fork
这里是对 fork 的调用，
or to call to kvmmapuser in fork.
或者调用 fork 中的 kvmmapuser 。
And it takes the n-,
它接受 n- ，
so the main question I think the most of you ask is,
我想大部分人问的主要问题是，
why does it have to be the new process kernel pagetable,
为什么一定要是新的进程内核页表，
why does it have to copy from the new process pagetable
为什么必须从新进程复制页表，
instead of from maybe the current process pagetable,
而不是当前进程页表，
because it's anyway an identical going forward,
因为不管怎样，之后都是一样的，
basically does it just replicates the,
基本上，它就是复制了，
user part of the pagetable
页表中的用户部分，
and so why can't we use the current pagetable for doing that.
那么为什么不使用当前页表来做这件事呢。
Why actually turns out the case,
为什么会出现这种情况，
you actually have to use the new,
你必须用新的，
you know the child's user part of the child user pagetable.
子进程的的用户页表。
Why is that the case.
为什么会这样呢？
Move you note what bug you get.
想一下你得到了什么 bug 。
When you get a remap error.
当你得到 remap 错误时。
You go, maybe not remap error maybe that too,
也许不是 remap 错误，可能是那个，
but I'm thinking of is not the remap one.
但我想的不是 remap 的那个。
Number of you tried it out,
你们中的一些人试过，
what was your personal experience.
你们感觉怎么样？
Anybody on the call who tried this out?
线上有人试过吗？
I remember what they resulting experiences,
我记得它们[导致的经历]，
I think the resulting and I did not have the bug with,
我觉得这个经历，我没有这个 bug ，
I think the resulting experience is that somewhere in usertest.
我认为体验是在 usertest 中的某个地方。
A particular usertest and do a lot of forking and executing,
一个特定的 usertest ，执行大量 fork 和执行，
you're going to get a problem,
你会得到一个问题，
and you get an error,
你会得到一个错误，
in the error, the thing that goes wrong is that,
在错误中，出错的是，
if you copy from the parent process,
如果从父进程复制，
if the parent process exits before the child process does,
如果父进程在子进程之前退出，
then the parent process page table will be completely clean up, right,
那么父进程页表会被彻底清理掉，
as we saw before,
正如我们之前看到的，
and then the child still has pointers to the parent process pagetable
然后，子进程仍然具有指向父进程页表的指针，
and so basically you're gonna,
所以基本上你会，
basically pages in this child process pagetable have been [treat]
基本上子进程中的页表已经处理过，
and they're still used,
而且仍在使用，
as a result in all kinds of bad behavior,
其结果就是各种不良行为，
because the kernel wanted free the page
因为内核释放页面，
actually writes ones in it everywhere,
实际上在里面写入 1 ，
for debugging reasons
为了调试的原因，
and so now basically you have
所以现在你有，
invalid you know ptes sitting in your kernel pagetable.
无效的 pte 在你的内核页表中。
Does that make sense.
这个能理解吗。
Okay, one more.
好的，下一个。
You can do to look at exec.c.
你可以查看 exec.c 。
In my solutions, are pretty straightforward,
在我的解决方案中，是很直截的，
always made no modifications to exec.
没有修改 exec 。
The only modification away,
唯一的修改是，
of course you know the first thing for, you know, part one,
当然，你知道第一部分的第一个，
and then here for part three,
接下来是第三部分，
which is basically mapping the new user pagetable into the kernel pagetable.
将新用户页表映射到内核页表。
Exec basically does,
exec 基本上是这样做的，
we built a new user address space
我们构建了一个新的用户地址空间，
and you know there's one line copies of new user address space into the kernel pagetable.
这一行复制新用户地址空间到内核页表。
And that's it.
就是这样。
Any questions.
有什么问题吗。
So, hope in the meantime,
所以，希望在此期间，
I've answered many of the questions that you submitted,
我已经回答了你们提交的很多问题，
we can look and see which ones,
我们可以看看有哪些，
there were a couple more questions
还有几个问题，
that I haven't talked about yet.
我还没讨论过。
So maybe we can look at those
所以也许我们可以看看那些，
or unless you have questions right away.
或者你有问题要问。
Um, don't we modify the growproc as well?
嗯，我们也要修改 growproc 吗？
Yes, there are a couple more changes are necessary,
是的，还有几处需要修改，
you know in sbrk or growproc.
在 sbrk 或 growproc 中。
There's a, I had a line right here,
有一个，我这里有一行，
similar style and there's presumably a similar change in.
类似的方式，也有类似的修改。
Again I might be it actually,
再说一次，[可能在这里]，
usually in it of course,
[经常在这里]，
it probably has to change.
它可能不得不改变。
Because you have to map that one page from the init code into the,
因为你必须将初始化代码中的一页映射到，
the kernel pagetable for you in that process.
进程中的内核页表。
Because the first process is special.
因为第一个进程很特别。
Okay so I'm gonna walk through some of the questions here
好的，现在我要浏览一下这里的一些问题，
and I put them on the screen,
我把它们放到屏幕上，
so you can helpful see them.
所以你们可以看到它们。
Actually I don't have to [] read them out completely.
其实我不一定要把它们全部读出来。
I think the first question is a question
第一个问题是，
that came up quite a bit about the pte_u bit flag,
关于 pte_u 标志位的，
I think we've covered this,
我想我们已经讨论过了，
we also cover the fact
我们还讨论了，
that it's not malicious,
它不是防止恶意行为的，
but it's mostly for debugging reasons.
而是主要出于调试的原因。
Similar question about like,
类似的问题，比如，
well if you're supervisor mode, can you do anything,
如果你在管理者模式，你能做任何事情吗，
because you can switch the satp,
因为你可以切换 satp ，
you can, um.
你可以，嗯。
And the answer is yes,
答案是肯定的，
also possible and so it really
也有可能，所以它是，
you know this u bit is not about
这个 u 标志位不是关于
the user program being protected from the kernel,
保护用户程序不受内核影响，
was really as a flag to help the kernel developer
实际上是作为标志位帮助内核开发人员，
and build the kernel.
用于构建内核。
One other specific RISC-V question,
另一个特殊的 RISC-V 问题，
which is why are they in trapframe proc.h,
为什么在 proc.h 的 trapframe 中，
the register should have been a in the strange order.
寄存器是这种奇怪的顺序。
And the reason that is,
原因是，
I think we mentioned this a little while ago,
我们之前提到过，
in the previous lecture,
在上一节课中，
basically there's something that's called the RISC-V compressed instruction set,
有一种叫做 RISC-V 压缩指令集的东西，
that has a set of fewer registers.
它使用一组较少的寄存器。
And, so you have to have more compact encoding of instructions.
所以你必须对指令进行更紧凑的编码。
And um, this strange ordering reflects the fact
那么这个奇怪的顺序反映了一个事实，
that they're basically to there's the compressed version,
它们是压缩版本，
which is some set of registers,
是某组寄存器，
and then sort of a compressed version,
是一种压缩版本，
which is what we're using,
我们正在使用的，
it has a complete set of registers.
它有一套完整的寄存器。
And the compression version, for example has s1 and s0,
而压缩版本，包含 s1 和 s0 ，
s0 and one,
s0 和 s1 ，
but not s2 to s11.
但没有 s2 到 s11 。
So that's the main reason.
所以这是主要原因。
I think I went through most of these questions,
我想我已经回答了大部分问题，
but if you see a question,
但是如果你看到一个问题，
that I should have covered and it didn't,
我应该讲却没有讲的问题，
please interrupt me
请打断我，
or if you ask a question I haven't covered yet,
或者你可以问我还没有讲到的问题，
please ask me.
请问我。
These questions are basically in order that submitted them,
这些问题基本上是按照提交的顺序，
so these were.
所以这些是。
Okay, here maybe.
好的，这里可能是。
So here's a question,
这有一个问题，
do operating system using hierarchical pagetables
对于使用分层页表的操作系统来说，
ever to set up the pagetable pages,
是否设置过页表页面，
so that the lower parts of the hierarchy, are these part shared.
让层次结构的较低部分是共享的。
And, you clearly saw my solution correct,
你看到我的解决方案，
I share the entries one to five eleven
我分享条目 1 到 511 ，
and so this is a standard trick,
这是一个标准的技巧，
and lots of operating systems do that.
很多操作系统都是这么做的。
I think we talked a little bit about this particular issue
我想我们讨论了一下这个特别的问题，
that is important that you switch to this main kernel pagetable,
切换到主内核页表是很重要的，
because scheduler,
因为调度程序，
there might be no user processes to run at all anymore,
可能根本没有要运行的用户进程，
in the scheduler of course still needs a pagetable,
在调度器中，当然还需要一个页表，
so it runs with the main kernel pagetable.
因此，它与主内核页表一起运行。
Question in the chat.
聊天中的问题。
Yeah go ahead.
好的，继续。
What is there when you pull up the chat.
聊天中的内容是什么。
I can read it.
我可以读出来。
Yeah I got it.
是的，我看到了。
So I think you know okay so the question is,
所以我想问题是，
note the RISC privilege specs saying
注意到 RISC 特权标准说到，
that part of the separation is to prevent bugs
隔离的那部分是为了防止 bug ，
that allow user program to make the kernel jump to arbitrary code in user space.
允许用户程序使内核跳转到用户空间中的任意代码。
Yes, that's a good point,
对，一个很好的观点，
yeah, so you know you can debate here,
所以你可以在这里辩论，
one of these is an isolation property or kernel debugging property.
是隔离属性或内核调试属性。
Clearly, the kernel should never
显然，内核永远不应该
jump into any part of the address, the user address space directly,
直接跳入用户地址空间的任何地址，
until you know I view this as a tool
除非我把它视为一种工具，
to help the kernel debug or catch those kinds of bugs.
来帮助内核调试或捕获这些类型的 bug 。
And some reasons why xv6 we also disable or set the u bit.
以及为什么对于 xv6 我们禁用或设置 u 标志位。
And don't allow the kernel to refer to any pages,
并且不允许内核引用任何（用户）页面，
that protects us, you know you did reference ever user address,
这防止我们，引用用户地址，
that the kernel would actually fault.
实际上内核会出错。
I think I've covered the scheduler point, too.
我想我也讨论了调度器。
So here's a question,
这里有一个问题，
how are pipes implemented in
xv6 中的管道是如何实现的，
and choose change to pagetable implemented the pgtlb lab
而且在 pgtlb 实验中修改页表，
effect this implementation.
怎样影响这个实现。
Um, so pipes are basically a buffering memory in the kernel.
嗯，管道基本上是内核中的一个缓冲内存。
And write, when you write your pipe,
还有写，当你写管道的时候，
basically calls copyin,
就是调用 copyin ，
and copyin copy the bytes from user space into the pipe,
copyin 将字节从用户空间复制到管道中，
and in some ways you know the whole part of the pgtbl lab,
在某些方面，页表实验的全部内容，
basically streamline that code.
简化了代码。
So you don't have to do many walks,
所以你不用调用很多 walk ，
when you actually you're write from user space into the pipe.
当你从用户空间写入管道时。
This is a question I think a lot of people ask,
这个问题我想很多人都在问，
you know like, why did uvmfree and freewalk,
为什么 uvmfree 和 freewalk ，
originally panic at a leaf.
会在叶节点引发错误。
And the reason is that,
原因是，
you know we put that in there,
我们把它放到那里，
because it broke, that was an indication
因为它坏了，这是一个迹象，
that an area in the xv6 would be broken,
xv6 中的一个区域将被破坏。
that's the invariant for unmodified xv6,
这是未修改的 xv6 的不变量，
in this particular case,
在这种情况下，
that is not true,
这不是真的，
and so, you have to basically get rid of the panic.
因此，你必须从根本上避免错误。
And realized that it was not important to panic,
意识到这个错误并不重要，
therefore, you should not get it there.
你不应该到达那里。
I think we talked quite a bit about,
我觉得我们讨论了不少，
why vm copy new's,
为什么 vm 复制新的，
why the new vm copy is good one.
为什么新的 vm 副本是好的。
Okay, here's another question,
好的，还有一个问题，
let's see this may be an interesting,
我们看一下，可能是一个有趣的，
one question was asked for more design question.
一个问题问到了更多的设计问题。
I need help have that picture.
我需要这张图片。
We look at the kernel address space where we limited,
我们看一下内核地址空间，
,
{} {}，
we limited user address user programs can be bigger
我们限制，用户地址用户程序可以更大，
user programs can grow through the CLINT address, no further.
用户程序最多可以增长到 CLIENT 地址。
Let's say we actually wanted to grow all the way to here.
假设我们实际上想要一路增长到这里。
How could we do that,
我们怎么能做到这一点，
what what,
怎么，
how should we change the design that would allow that.
我们应该如何改变设计来允许这个。
Anybody.
有人知道吗。
Could we remap the stuff,
我们是否可以重新映射这些东西，
like CLINT PLIC and UART.
比如 CLINT PLIC 和 UART ？
Yeah, where would you map that,
是的，你会在哪里映射，
so where if you want to do,
你想在哪里，
free up basically that part of the address space,
来释放地址空间的那部分，
where what could you do.
你能在哪里做（映射）。
Map into like a custom thing,
映射到一个地方，
before KERNBASE and after,
在 KERNBASE 之前和，
like before PHYSTOP, and after KERNBASE.
在 PHYSTOP 之前和 KERNBASE 之后。
Yeah, or maybe it's better to after PHYSTOP,
是啊，或者更好的是在 PHYSTOP 之后，
here's a huge amount of free space.
这里有大量的自由空间。
Like address space isn't used like this,
比如地址空间没有使用，
from here to there is basically used for physical memory.
从这里到那里都是用于物理内存。
And we basically could setup mappings here,
我们可以在这里设置映射，
for example we could put the UART here,
例如，我们可以把 UART 放在这里，
UART0,
UART0 ，
we can put just about PHYSTOP page,
我们放在 PHYSTOP 旁边，
and basically set up a mapping
建立一个映射，
that maps in that particular physical address, right,
映射到那个特定的物理地址，
then now will free up this mapping
那么现在将释放这些映射，
and we could use it for user space,
我们可以把它用作用户空间，
so similarly we could do that for UART0
同样，我们也可以对 UART0 执行此操作，
or VIRTIO_disk, for PLIC and CLINT.
或 VIRTIO_disk ， PLIC 和 CLINT 。
And real kernels do that.
真正的内核是这样做的。
Does that make sense.
这个能理解吗。
Is it isn't that problematic though,
这没有问题吗，
cause we would want the same same mapping
因为我们会想要同样的映射，
as the original kernel pagetable has.
像原来的内核页表一样。
Well, we have to do it in every every kernel pagetable,
好的，我们需要对每个内核页表做这个，
we have copies,
我们要复制，
we have to map it everywhere at that particular location.
我们必须把在特定的位置把它映射到任何地方。
I'm not sure that is,
我不确定是不是，
not sure I answered your question,
不确定是否回答了你的问题，
but I don't think that's a problem.
但是我不认为这是一个问题。
I see, so you do that mapping also in the original.
我明白了，所以你也在原来的（页表）中做这个映射。
Yeah we have to do those in the original one.
是的，我们也得在原来的做这些。
It does easier if the whole kernel uniformly
这很简单，让整个内核统一，
thinks about UART0 sitting at the top.
让 UART0 位于顶端。
You know, a number of people ask
很多人问到，
why do we map the kernel stacks high up.
为什么我们要将内核堆栈映射到高位置。
What is the reason for that.
那是什么原因呢？
Like in procinit, we map these kernel stacks high up
在 procinit 中，我们将这些内核堆栈映射到高处，
and if you did the copy approach,
如果你采用复制的方法，
you actually have to modify procinit,
你实际上需要修改 procinit ，
actually copy over that mapping.
复制这个映射。
And why sitting in up high virtual address space?
为什么要在虚拟地址空间高位置？
Anybody?
有人知道吗？
Is it specifically because the the stacks in RISC-V grow downwards,
是不是因为 RISC-V 中的堆栈向下增长，
so you place it high in the address space,
所以你把它放在地址空间的高处，
that it has space to grow downwards.
让它有向下增长的空间。
Yeah, how much this direction how much page does it have to grow downwards?
是的，这个方向，要向下增长多少页呢？
That shouldn't matter, because it's just one page, right.
那应该没关系，因为它只有一页，对吧。
Yeah it's only one page,
是的，只有一页，
so what happens if you grow on one page?
那么如果你增长超过一页会发生什么呢？
You run into the guard page, correct.
你到了守护页，对吧。
And the guard page not mapped
而守护页没有映射，
and so the kernel will panic,
因此内核将会错误，
which is better than actually writing over its data structures.
这比覆盖数据结构要好。
So the reason it's high up is
所以它在高处的原因是，
because we put a guard page below it.
因为我们在它下面放了一个守护页。
Is there actually any physical memory associated with that guard page.
守护页有没有关联的物理内存？
No.
没有。
No, there's no physical memory associated with the guard page,
是的，没有与守护页关联的物理内存，
so that's one of the cool things about putting it high
所以把它放得很高的一件很酷的事情，
is that we can put a guard page below it
我们可以放一个守护页面在它下面，
that actually doesn't really consume any physical memory.
实际上不会消耗任何物理内存。
Okay.
好的。
Does that make sense.
能理解吗。
Also, basically the stack staff page will be physical somewhere,
堆栈页面在物理内存的某个地方，
but the guard page won't.
但守护页页不是？
Exactly.
没错。
Again, one of the cool things you can do with virtual memory.
再说一次，这是使用虚拟内存可以做的很酷的事情之一。
Is it possible to overshoot the guard page.
有没有可能超过守护页。
That's a great question,
这是个很好的问题
you know one of one for example is
举个例子，
you know, you allocated the guar-,
你分配了（守护页），
a buffer on the stack
一个堆栈上的缓冲区，
that actually is [] bigger than the guard page, correct,
它比守护页大，对吧，
and sort of goes into the next kernel stack page.
然后进入下一个内核堆栈页面。
And yeah you would have a serious bug.
是的，你会有一个严重的 bug 。
Most likely you will run into that anyway,
你很可能会遇到这样的情况，
because you would use the first entries that buffer,
因为你将使用缓冲的第一个条目，
and then you will get the page fault.
然后就会得到页面错误。
When you get lucky.
当你走运的时候。
So this is not a bulletproof kernel debugging technique,
所以这不是一种绝对有效的内核调试技术，
but it has proved to be extremely effective.
但事实证明它非常有效。
Great question.
好问题。
Any more questions.
还有什么问题吗。
We'll go back to the list.
我们回到（问题）列表上。
See, we have a couple more minutes
我们还有几分钟，
and then actually we have one more minute.
实际上还有一分多钟。
I have a question,
我有个问题，
so once we have our kernel pagetable for the processes,
一旦我们有了进程的内核页表，
does that mean that in the trap code,
这是否意味着在 trap 代码中，
we don't need to switch pagetables.
我们不需要切换页表。
I think the great question, a good design question,
我认为是一个好问题，一个好的设计问题，
and the answer is yes, you don't need it right,
答案是肯定的，你不需要它，
because, the main reason that
因为，主要原因是
the kernel or in trampoline code,
内核或者 trampoline 代码，
we go through all this trouble
我们经历这些麻烦，
is because we have to copy the user,
是因为我们必须复制用户（页表），
we have to switch from the kernel pagetable to the user pagetable,
我们必须从内核页表切换到用户页表，
the user pagetable or a pagetable doesn't have the rest of the kernel map.
用户页表或没有其他内核映射的页表。
Um, and so, downside.
嗯，所以，缺点是。
Wait, I'm not sure that's true,
等等，我不确定这是不是正确的，
because the kernel needs to have the user block,
因为内核需要有，
user flag on set.
设置用户标志。
Yeah, okay so there's a couple of points I wanted to make,
是的，好的，我有几点想说，
so in principle, you could simplify,
原则上，你可以简化，
let me put it this way,
我这么说吧，
you can simplify entry and exit,
你可以简化进入退出，
if you have a single pagetable that maps the user in the kernel
如果你在内核中有一个单独的页表映射到用户，
in a single pagetable,
在单独页表中，
because then you don't have to switch,
那样你就不用切换了，
you will have to make a couple more modifications to xv6
你需要对 xv6 进行更多修改，
to make that happen.
才能做到这一点。
But in principle you could
但是，原则上是可以的，
and in fact Linux until very recently used,
事实上，直到最近 Linux 使用，
you know this sort of strategy
这种策略，
of where the kernel and the user code are sitting in a single pagetable,
内核和用户代码位于单个页表中，
in relying on basically u bit,
依赖 u 标志位，
you know to make sure that the,
来确保，
the user program couldn't actually modify any kernel pages.
用户程序无法修改任何内核页面。
And the entry exit code in that case is slightly simpler,
在这种情况下，进入退出代码稍微简单一些，
because you don't have to switch pagetables
因为你不必切换页表，
when you enter or leave the kernel.
当你进入或离开内核时。
One thing that happened with
可能会发生一件事，
for example the meltdown attack,
比如，熔断攻击，
if you might have [] side channel attack,
你可能受到侧通道攻击，
in response to the actually side channel attack,
针对侧通道攻击，
Linux switch or as another mode of running,
Linux 切换或作为另一种模式运行，
there are two modes of running, one's called kpti mode.
有两种运行模式，一种称为 kpti 模式。
And in that mode, basically that reflects basically what xv6 does.
在该模式下，反映了 xv6 所做的事情。
We're having a separate pagetable for the kernel
我们有一个单独的内核页表，
and a separate pagetable for user space.
和一个单独的用户空间页表。
But I still don't understand why that's that works,
但我还是不明白这为什么管用，
so let's say the per user process and the kernel use the same pagetable
因此，假设每个用户进程和内核使用相同的页表，
if the user memory has to have the user bit set,
如果用户内存必须设置用户位，
the kernel will not be able to access that user memory right.
内核将无法访问该用户内存。
OK, the.
好的。
Okay, on Intel processors that is not the rule,
好的，在英特尔处理器上这不是[规则]，
so for example, Intel processors, if u bit set,
因此，英特尔处理器，如果设置了 u 标志位，
the kernel could still write and read that page.
内核仍然可以写入和读取那个页。
Oh, that's just a RISC-V thing.
哦，那只是一个 RISC-V 的事情。
And even on the RISC-V, you can change it,
即使在 RISC-V 上，你也可以修改它，
there's a bit in the sstatus register,
在 sstatus 寄存器中有一位，
you can set that to some bit
你可以将其设置为某个位，
and if you set that
如果你设置了它，
then basically in kernel mode,
然后处于内核模式，
the u bit is ignored.
u 标志位会被忽略。
Okay so you're telling me that there's just one bit in this [] processor
好的，你是说这个处理器中的一位，
that made me stay up four hours later.
让我晚了四个小时才睡。
Yes, I'm very sorry about that,
是的，我对此非常抱歉，
I should have known that.
我早该知道的。
When you report,
当你报告后，
it reminded me of a bug,
它让我想起了一个 bug ，
that I actually had during the summer,
我在夏天遇到的，
it was exactly that bug,
就是那个 bug ，
but I forgot about it.
但是我忘了这件事。
So my apology for that.
所以，我对此道歉。
No, it's okay,
不，没关系，
it was a, it was fun figuring it out for sure,
这是一个很有趣的事情，
but I at some point I was just like
但是在某个时候我就像，
okay like either I'm crazy or something completely wrong,
好吧，要么是我疯了，要么是完全错了，
so I'm just gonna go to sleep
所以我去睡觉了，
and submit this piazza post
然后提交了这个 piazza 问题，
and hopefully when I wake up, someone will answer,
希望当我醒来的时候，有人会回答，
fortunately that was the case,
幸运的是，情况就是这样。
so I was able to just continue [write off] when I when I did.
所以我可以继续[]。
Okay so I think we ran overtime a little bit,
好的，我想我们有点超时了，
hopefully this was helpful
希望这些有帮助，
and reaffirm things with virtual memory.
并回顾了虚拟内存的东西。
I think it's important to do,
我觉得这件事很重要，
because we're going to get three more labs involving virtual memory.
因为我们还会有三个涉及虚拟内存的实验。
And my hope is that,
我希望是，
after this one you know there's going to be easier than this experience.
在这一次之后，会比这次经历更容易。
Can I ask something very quick?
我能问个小问题吗？
Yeah yeah I'm I'm staying on,
是的，我要留下来，
so everybody wants to stay on and ask more questions,
所以如果有人想留下来，问更多问题，
please feel free to do,
请随意，
so if you need to go to the next class, please go.
如果你需要上下一节课，也可以走。
So basically, in all the labs,
所以基本上，在所有的实验里，
like there's a lot of mention of,
有很多提到，
like oh we, this might be useful in future labs,
比如，这在未来的实验里可能会有用，
but we never actually use any of the code that we write,
但是实际上我们从来没有用过我们写的任何代码，
like what's what's the plan on that,
那个计划是什么，
like should we just import our code from a previous lab
我们是否应该只从之前的实验导入代码，
or like I don't want to because what if it's bug,
或者我不想那样，因为如果有 bug ，
I don't wanna you know impact the next lab.
我不想影响下一个实验。
Yeah, so, one reason we don't do it,
是的，所以，我们不这么做的一个原因是，
you know why, why the build labs don't build on each other,
为什么实验不是建立在彼此之上，
even though they could,
即使它们可以，
is to avoid basic dependencies,
就是为了避免基本依赖关系，
like if you had a bug in earlier lab,
比如，如果你在前面的实验中有个 bug ，
that was not exposed by usertests
没有被 usertests 检查出，
or any of other tests,
或任何其他测试，
but will be exposed to that new lab,
但是会暴露在那个新的实验里，
then you know be painful.
那你会很痛苦。
The reason I'm mentioning that is
我提到的原因是，
that basically the real thing what's going on,
这是真实的事情如何发生，
is we're going to do more stuff with pagetables.
我们要用页表做更多的事情。
For example, this lab looks at simplifying copyin,
例如，这个实验考虑简化 copyin ，
later labs, we look at change to sbrk,
在后面的实验中，我们考虑对 sbrk 的修改，
basically we're far gonna to the changes you made to the kernel for his lab.
基本上，我们离你在这个实验中对内核的修改很远。
But you know the fact that you've been thinking about
但是你知道，你一直考虑，
kernel pagetable user page tables so much, will help you.
内核页表，用户页表，会对你有帮助。
Plus, it really helps you experience debugging these kinds of problems,
另外，它真的可以帮助你经历调试这类问题，
due to incorrect pagetables.
由于页表不正确（的问题）。
Okay I just want to make sure
好的，我只是想确认一下，
that it's not like I'm missing out,
我没有错过，
because I didn't copy over my xargs code from lab one or something.
因为我没有从实验一复制我的 xargs 代码或别的东西。
Decided to purpose that the labs were not dependent on each other.
实验目标不同，它们互不依赖。
Okay, thanks, see you on wednesday.
好的，谢谢，星期三见。
Wednesday.
星期三见。
I had a follow up on my question about mapping,
我有一个关于映射更进一步的问题，
mapping using the modification from the pagetable lab,
映射使用页表实验中的修改，
would it be then needed to
那么是否需要
have the trampoline maps in the user pagetables.
trampoline 映射到用户页表。
Okay so I haven't really thought this through.
好的，我没有想过这个。
So if you've kernels, let's say the kernel exits,
所以如果你，假设内核存在，
so let's say we have join one single pagetable
因此，假设我们已经关联了一个页表，
as one here shown, correct.
就像这里显示的一样。
And, we're jumping out of the kernel through userret.
并且，我们通过 userret 跳出内核。
In our goal is to we're still running in kernel mode,
我们的目标是，我们还在内核模式下运行，
so this page certainly accessible, correct, in by the kernel.
所以内核当然可以访问这个页面。
The guard page,
守护页，
I'll show you,
我展示的，
do not the guard page, when I'm saying
不是守护页，
the trampoline pages there,
是 trampoline 页面，
and presumably somewhere,
很可能在某个地方，
we need to map maybe the.
我们需要映射，或许。
Well, the user trapframe,
好的，用户 trapframe ，
we don't really have access to anyway,
我们并不能访问，
because we're running kernel mode,
因为我们运行的是内核模式，
we know where it sits in the proc structure,
我们知道它在 proc 结构中，
or we can get it.
或者我们可以得到它。
So I think we can just exit.
所以我想我们可以退出。
And when you return,
当你回来的时候，
the user code can just run,
用户代码可以直接运行，
you know we of course the u bit is.
当然 u 标志位是。
But u bit is always set pages
但是 u 标志位总是设置页面，
that actually sit in the user space,
位于用户空间中，
so that's fine too,
所以这也是好的，
so when we enter the kernel back in,
因此，当我们重新进入内核时，
we're still with this pagetable,
我们仍然使用这个页表，
that pagetable already has all the kernel that mapped.
这个页表现在已经映射了所有内核。
And we can just you know copy, you know the registers
我们可以直接复制寄存器，
that we need to save into the proc structure directly.
我们需要保存到 proc 结构中的（寄存器）。
Instead of having to go through separate page
而不必查找单独的页面，
with the proc structure in it.
里面有 proc 结构。
So I believe the change will be pretty straightforward.
所以我相信修改会相当直接。
Okay I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Of course, I could be wrong.
当然，我可能是错的。
Yeah I'm now gonna try it now.
好的，我现在去试一下。